export const CHRISTIANRELIGIOUSSTUDIESA2023 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. Go, tell your lord, Behold, Elijah is here. Obadiah understood Elijah’s command as",
A: "a rebellion against king Ahab.",
B: "ingratitude on the part of Elijah.",
C: "an attempt to get him killed.",
D: "a call to contest on Mount Carmel.",
answer: "C. an attempt to get him killed.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. The proposal to store the fifth part of the agricultural produce during the seven years of bumperharvest in Egypt was the suggestion of",
A: "Pharaoh.",
B: "Potiphar.",
C: "Joseph.",
D: "the butler.",
answer: "C. Joseph.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. Jesus admonished Christians to forgive their neighbours’ sins for",
A: "seventeen times seven.",
B: "as many times as possible.",
C: "a limited number of times.",
D: "seventy-seven times seven.",
answer: "D. seventy-seven times seven.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. According to Jesus, forgiving those who offend us is a major condition for",
A: "enjoying God’s favour.",
B: "obtaining divine forgiveness.",
C: "enjoying God’s protection.",
D: "obtaining God’s grace.",
answer: "B. obtaining divine forgiveness.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. What was Josiah’s immediate reaction when the book of the law was read to him? He",
A: "fell down and collapsed.",
B: "assembled his elders.",
C: "rent his clothes.",
D: "sent envoys to Huldah.",
answer: "C. rent his clothes.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. According to Joseph, God duplicated Pharaoh’s dreams to prove",
A: "His determination to punish Pharaoh.",
B: "that Israel would surely cross the Red Sea.",
C: "His supremacy over Egyptian gods.",
D: "that what He has purposed would come to pass.",
answer: "D. that what He has purposed would come to pass.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. The temptation of Jesus focused on the following aspects of social life except",
A: "material wants.",
B: "jealousy.",
C: "egoism.",
D: "supreme authority.",
answer: "B. jealousy.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. Ahab was adjudged the worst king to have ever ruled Israel because of his involvement in",
A: "idolatry.",
B: "adultery",
C: "theft.",
D: "murder.",
answer: "A. idolatry.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. Saul’s aim of going to Damascus was to",
A: "stone Christians to death.",
B: "preach about Jesus and salvation to the Jews.",
C: "bind Christians back to Jerusalem as captives",
D: "convince other disciples of his conversion.",
answer: "C. bind Christians back to Jerusalem as captives.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. The request Barak made to Deborah to accompany him to battle with Jabin exposed Barak’s",
A: "unwillingness to lead Israel.",
B: "cowardice and lack of faith.",
C: "disrespect for women in leadership.",
D: "readiness to die for Israel.",
answer: "B. cowardice and lack of faith.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. Which of the following was the reason for which the believers were scattered abroad after thedeath of stephen?",
A: "The young church could not meet their socio economic need.",
B: "The Roman authorities banned all religious gathering in jeruselem",
C: "There was a great persecution against the church in jeruselem",
D: "Jesus had instructed them to spread the gospel to all parts of the world.",
answer: "C. There was a great persecution against the church in Jerusalem.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. Fear not. stand firm, and see the salvation of the Lord. which he will work for you today, ......On which of the following occasions did Moses make the above statement? When",
A: "the Israelites requested for a new leadership back to Egypt.",
B: "God commanded him to raise his rod over the Red Sea.",
C: "the Israclites were trapped between the host of Egypt and the Red Sea.",
D: "the Israelites faced hunger and death at the wilderness of Zin.",
answer: "C. the Israelites were trapped between the host of Egypt and the Red Sea.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. Which of the following lessons can be Icarnt from the devotion of members in the carly church? The",
A: "Speaking of tongues during worship",
B: "Selling of properties and sowing seed to the lord",
C: "worshipping in oneness of spirit and lifting of others",
D: "appointment of deacons to serve tables",
answer: "C. worshipping in oneness of spirit and lifting of others.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. Samuel’s inability to recognize the voice of God when he was under Eli was due to the fact that",
A: "he had expected to see vis.ons instead.",
B: "the voice of God was rare in those days.",
C: "his relationship with God was cordial.",
D: "the word of God had not yet been revealed to him.",
answer: "D. the word of God had not yet been revealed to him.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. Peter advised the Christians in exile to maintain good conduct and practice virtues so that thegentiles",
A: "would embrace their faith.",
B: "would fear and respect them.",
C: "may honour and glorify God.",
D: "may also change their behaviour.",
answer: "C. may honor and glorify God.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. The fear entertained by the Israelites after the report of the Spies was as a result of the",
A: "great stature of the sons of Anak.",
B: "military might of Canaan.",
C: "location of the Canaan cities.",
D: "faithlessness of the Israelites.",
answer: "A. great stature of the sons of Anak.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. Luke’s account of the call of the first three disciples involved the use of",
A: "parable.",
B: "force. .",
C: "diplomacy.",
D: "miracle.",
answer: "D. miracle.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. Now go and smite Amalek, and utterly destroy all that they have... What occasioned thiscommand by God? The Amalekites",
A: "oppressed the Israelites on their way from Egypt to Canaan.",
B: "supported the Philistines to capture the Ark of God at Aphek.",
C: "encouraged the Egyptians to oppress the Israelites as slaves.",
D: "failed to repent from their sins.",
answer: "A. oppressed the Israelites on their way from Egypt to Canaan.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. Are you the only visitor to Jerusalem who does not know the things that have happened therein these days? This remark was made to indict Jesus of",
A: "political apathy.",
B: "religious intolerance.",
C: "spiritual laxity.",
D: "social indifference.",
answer: "D. social indifference.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. Follow me, and leave the dead to bury their own dead. By this statement Jesus meant thatdiscipleship involves",
A: "disregarding all family members",
B: "refusing to bury the dead.",
C: "giving priority to God in all things.",
D: "preaching the gospel all the time.",
answer: "C. giving priority to God in all things.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. Take off the rings of gold which are in the ears of your wives..., and bring them to me. Thisact was a show of the people’s",
A: "atheism.",
B: "theocracy.",
C: "apostasy.",
D: "theism.",
answer: "C. apostasy.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. Which of the following is a major factor that led to the appointment of the seven deacons? The",
A: "increase in the number of the brethren.",
B: "arrival of the Grecian Jews to Jerusalem.",
C: "shortage of food shared for the needy.",
D: "need for the apostles to concentrate on the preaching of the gospel.",
answer: "A. increase in the number of the brethren.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. The revelation Amos received from God indicated the songs of",
A: "lamentation.",
B: "petition.",
C: "thanksgiving.",
D: "praise.",
answer: "A. lamentation.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. Which of the following was Peter’s reason for running out of the courtyard to weep bitterly?",
A: "He could not fulfil his vows to Jesus.",
B: "The bystanders identified him as a disciple.",
C: "He feared Jesus might be guilty.",
D: "The cock crowed twice.",
answer: "D. The cock crowed twice.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. Rehum’s petition to King Artaxerxes was meant to",
A: "prevent future rebellion in the city.",
B: "be lenient to the inhabitants of the city.",
C: "finance the construction of the temple.",
D: "order cessation of the construction of the temple.",
answer: "D. order cessation of the construction of the temple.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. So, could you not watch with me one hour? This statement by Jesus implies that Christians should",
A: "have sound mind to judge events.",
B: "recognize his voice.",
C: "be able to overcome temptations.",
D: "be able to withstand danger.",
answer: "C. be able to overcome temptations.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. John the Baptist’s reluctance 10 baptize Jesus was borne out of the fact that Jesus was",
A: "without sin.",
B: "hota gentile.",
C: "the son of God.",
D: "vers spiritual.",
answer: "A. without sin.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. This at last is bone of nty bones and flesh of my flesh, This statement shows that man",
A: "could now see clearly.",
B: "sees the possibility of happiness.",
C: "was deriding the animals.",
D: "was showing eratitude to God.",
answer: "D. was showing gratitude to God.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. Which of the following gills God gave to Solomon had conditions attached?",
A: "Riches",
B: "Fruitiuiness",
C: "Long life",
D: "Honour",
answer: "C. Long life.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. Which of the following was the justification for Hosea’s marriage to a harlot? To",
A: "teach the Israelites lessons on faithfulness.",
B: "point out the punishment for aduitery.",
C: "appreciate the blessings of a faithful wife.",
D: "relate through experience the love God had for Israel.",
answer: "D. relate through experience the love God had for Israel.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. I was Joppa praying in a trance I was a vision. What was the outcome of this vision?",
A: "The gentil were circumcised for the fisrt time.",
B: "The gentil also received the word of God.",
C: "Peter ate forbidden food for the first time.",
D: "Peter was accused by believers in Jerusalem.",
answer: "B. The Gentiles also received the word of God.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. It can be inferred that Solomon’s fall as a king was as a result ofwealth and fame.",
A: "wealth and fame.",
B: "peace and international relations.",
C: "pleasure and excitement.",
D: "fame and power.",
answer: "A. wealth and fame.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. To ascertain the suitability of Joshua as a successor to Moses, Eleazar the priest was commanded",
A: "seek the views of the elders.",
B: "consult God on Mount Sinai.",
C: "consult God through divination.",
D: "fast and pray.",
answer: "C. consult God through divination.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. The observation of sabbath is relevant today because it enables humankind to",
A: "think about worldly things.",
B: "have leisure time.",
C: "be diligent at work. ‘",
D: "be hard working.",
answer: "B. have leisure time.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. The treatment given to the rich and the poor in an assembly was used by James to teach against",
A: "partiality.",
B: "impartiality.",
C: "greed.",
D: "laziness.",
answer: "A. partiality.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. After creation, God provided food for man by instructing him to eat",
A: "bread without yeast on specific days.",
B: "only clean animals and birds.",
C: "every tree and plant with seed in its fruit",
D: "all animals and birds.",
answer: "C. every tree and plant with seed in its fruit.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. The Israelite maid who introduced Naaman to Elisha for healing exhibited the trail of",
A: "compassion and faith.",
B: "love and loyalty.",
C: "charity and love.",
D: "patience and loyalty.",
answer: "A. compassion and faith.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. Which of the following was the reason for which Joshua was mandated to meditate on the book of the law day and night? To",
A: "have an encounter with God.",
B: "be successful and prosperous.",
C: "be an acceptable sacrifice.",
D: "annihilate all his enemies.",
answer: "B. be successful and prosperous.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. The sons of E1i demonstrated contempt for the Lord’s offering when they",
A: "slept with the women at the temple gate.",
B: "took raw meat before the fat was burnt.",
C: "took bribe and perverted justice.",
D: "disregarded the advice of their father.",
answer: "B. took raw meat before the fat was burnt.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. Which of the following lessons can be learnt from David's response to Nathan's accusation?",
A: "The consequense of sin cannot beb avoided.",
B: "No one can run away from one's sin.",
C: "One must be bold to tell the truth to thos who sin.",
D: "progress is from God.",
answer: "C. One must be bold to tell the truth to those who sin.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. The treaty King Solomon made with Tyre signified that",
A: "obedience to God brings success.",
B: "progress requires peace and unity.",
C: "every sin is punishable.",
D: "progress is from God.",
answer: "B. progress requires peace and unity.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. Which of the following criteria was meant to be fulfilled by the successor of Judas Iscariot? Should be a",
A: "kinsman to Jesus.",
B: "witness of Jesus from birth to crucifixion.",
C: "witness to Jesus’ transfiguration. *",
D: "witness of Christ from baptism to ascension",
answer: "D. witness of Christ from baptism to ascension.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. Peter states that while Christians suffering is for a while, the glory of God will be",
A: "for all people.",
B: "enjoyed eternally.",
C: "enjoyed temporarily.",
D: "for selected Christians.",
answer: "B. enjoyed eternally.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. According to James, a pure and undefiled religion is characterized by the following except",
A: "bridginfg one's tongue",
B: "keeoing oneself unstained  from the world.",
C: "being a hearer of the word not a doer.",
D: "visiting widows and orphans.",
answer: "C. being a hearer of the word not a doer.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. The most important lesson outlined in Hosea’s message is God’s",
A: "punishment ros n.",
B: "everlasting ies ankind.",
C: "love for unfaithful wives.",
D: "desire for true repentance.",
answer: "D. desire for true repentance.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. Elijah rebuked Ahab for possessing Naboth’s vineyard because Ahab",
A: "had absolute power over all Jands.",
B: "did not use his power according to divine laws.",
C: "had a vineyard near his palace for use.",
D: "allowed the worship of foreign gods on the vineyard.",
answer: "B. did not use his power according to divine laws.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. Which of the following was a major reform carried out by Josiah in the defunct Northern Kingdom?",
A: "destroyed th calves and Asherah.",
B: "converted al aal to a place of convenience.",
C: "removed the bronze serpent in the temple",
D: "reinstated the celebration of the passover",
answer: "D. reinstated the celebration of the Passover.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. In which of the following ways did Nehemiah respond to the opposition.cf Sanballat and Tobiah? He",
A: "committed them to God.",
B: "pleaded that they should join him.",
C: "fasted and prayed for days.",
D: "reported them to the King.",
answer: "A. committed them to God.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. Therefore King Darius signed the document and interdict. This implies that the law",
A: "cannot be revoked.",
B: "was made for Jews only.",
C: "was for Persians only.",
D: "is faulty and needed amendment.",
answer: "A. cannot be revoked.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. As a chosen race and holy nation, Peter mandated the exiled Christians to",
A: "support one another.",
B: "abstain from corruption.",
C: "worship God faithfully.",
D: "make known the good works of Jesus.",
answer: "D. make known the good works of Jesus.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},


]